What questions should one ask about Cedric today?
There are so many.
But I'll start just with one.
It's the mode of thinking.
What architecture does.
And architecture is also about questioning the society in which we live.
And it is also about providing, inventing questions and providing potential answers.
Cedric did it in an extraordinary manner.
And I'm still, 50 years later, I'm still interested in this.
At the same time, something else has happened today, which is not necessarily for
the better,
which is the over-reliance to simply hyper-realist images, which go exactly against
the thinking.
And so this question of finding a mode of notation that allows you to develop an
argument,
And as opposed to finding simply hyper-realist renderings that provide the supposed
answers
to questions that were never asked, I think that's perhaps one of the questions that
is being raised
by this discussion that we have about Cedric these days. As you know, I was always
quite
interested in what Cedric was doing already at the time and yes indeed it has
had an influence and probably still now in some sort of a way. Namely that
the architect is there, yes, to ask questions. Not necessarily to provide any
any answer that can satisfy the market or a particular client.
It's really looking at society as it is
and seeing opportunities for invention.
I'll take two projects that we all know,
the Fun Palace or the Potteries Thinkbelt.
In themselves, they are not a burning need
for the society at the time.
Nobody was thinking about it.
but it was there.
And the potential that was raised,
thanks to asking these questions,
was enormous and had an influence
that did reverberate for 20, 30 years after that.
I found a profoundly, let's say,
a introspective person
that was simultaneously, constantly walking on a tight rope.
In other words, when he would give lectures, now in public,
the mode of lecturing, which if you've ever tried,
of using individual cards which have statements
and shuffling the cards in any possible order,
and then trying to develop an argument out of the random appearance of each of
those questions or comments is not an easy thing to do. It requires an agility
of the mind which he possessed to a great degree. So when he was working
around certain theme that I was familiar with it was certainly an easy you know
dialogue but when he was taking other courses of conversation such as cooking
or things of this sort then he would get me completely lost.
Cédric's most significant project, I mean I would say the project of his life, i.e.
trying to construct architecture as a form of philosophical endeavor, as a
form of research, and I would use in my own words as a form of knowledge and not
simply as knowledge of form. After that we can go and look at a series of
of individual projects and we can depending on the context in which we
we operate we can say this this or that but I think the larger issue is rather
considering that architecture can be something more than simply the answer to
one specific you know question well you know the history of architecture is
filled with people who had a lot of influence and built little. Take
Piranesi for example, a major, major influence. Take Boulet, Ledoux and Lequeux,
three of the so-called utopian socialists in France, enormous influence.
Take in the at the time of same periods as Cedric was active, people like
yeah I mean take Virilio and Paran with the oblique function that's later on
Jona Friedman for example. So you have many many people who had an influence
beyond the act of building, and I would say that even a lesson to learn about
what architecture is. Architecture is a mode of thinking and not only a mode of
building. And I think this is really important, and there are some cultures
and some natures that refuse the idea that architecture is a mode of thinking.
I remember one famous Pritzker Prize architect saying that at the end all the
writing disappears only the building remains. I would might I might want to
argue the opposite. Even though I think both of them the building and the
writing tend to reinforce one another and that's probably what makes it the
most interesting. I think if the opportunity had a reason for him to
build more than he has I think he would have seized upon the opportunity. The
reason is that building actually helps you phrase further questions, right? In my
particular case I've always found fascinating the back and forth between
not only theory and practice but between certain way to raise questions, certain
way to answers which are not the only ones and then that bouncing from
the real to the virtual, from the real to the totally, totally theoretical, is an
incredibly
powerful mode of doing things.
So I think that it would have been good for Cedric to find himself in the situation
of
having the shoes in the mud and raising other questions.
I won the competition of the Parc de la Villette.
And at the time, at the beginning of the competition,
I won it as a master plan.
In other words, I was to organize not only
some of my own building, but have also
other buildings of people who would join us.
So I started to invite some of my friends.
And there was John Haydack.
There was Peter Eisenman that I paired with Jack Derrida.
And there was, of course, Cedric.
And Cedric was very excited about the idea of doing it.
He was very, actually very supportive of my project.
So everything seems to go well.
However, it was also a time when money was getting short.
And the government was changing.
It was an extremely complicated affair.
And at the time, it had been said
that it should be something which is now familiar
to our ears, a PPP, a public-private partnership
between the people who would sponsor the building
that I had asked Cedric to work on.
What I had asked Cedric to work on was a greenhouse.
And that greenhouse had to be financed simultaneously
by a large horticultural, not quite multinational corporation,
but a large operator selling seeds and trees and things
of this sort.
So Cedric designed, actually, if I remember correctly,
two schemes for a site that I had given him.
The principle was they were the greater fallas,
and then you would attach to each of the Follets
one of those buildings done by another architect.
So in the case of Cedric's greenhouse,
it was actually quite beautiful, very straightforward.
It was a half cylinder with activities happening
at different levels within it.
In many ways, sometimes I say laughingly
that the zoo here in Paris,
I just finished the Paris Zoo a few months ago,
that the greenhouse has some bit of an homage
to Cedric in its simplicity.
Unfortunately, back to La Villette,
the arrangement between the person
or the company that was supposed to finance Cedric project
and the park could never be finalized
and the project never went beyond,
you know, call it design development.
One thing which is very clear about the scene
that anybody would enter arriving in London
in, say, 1970, 1971.
Most schools of architecture
used to have a very clear idea of what architecture was.
It was directly a reflection, almost a mirror image, of what was happening in
practice.
Practice and the whole history of the modern movement was dictating what was
happening in the school.
you were learning in the schools what practice had done before you. Arriving
in London at that time, suddenly, or maybe not in London, maybe at the A, suddenly
it was something which was completely the reverse, where the students were
asked to write the program, the students were asked to write the assignments. In
in the diploma school for a year,
they struggled trying to find what will we do?
What do we propose?
To me, that was absolutely fantastic
because that was completely reversing the logic,
which is still similar in a lot of places.
The architect provides services
that are required by the client.
In the case of the A, that was the other way around.
the architect was to determine what some of the,
what were the needs of society.
And now you realize that that was exactly in sync
with what Cedric was doing.
But ultimately, you know, you could say,
and some people might disagree,
but you might say that Archigram,
when they were designing walking cities,
or plugging cities, or instant cities,
were also suggesting what society might need or want.
So there was a spirit of invention
which was putting the responsibility
back onto the architect,
rather than saying, oh, we do what we're being asked.
And I think this is important,
and that's something which is still,
I do believe, valid today.
If one was to ask oneself today whether this spirit is still alive,
I would say yes, it's up to you entirely.
And there are fortunately a number of architects
who will redefine the question that has been asked to them.
There are a number of architects who will say,
hey, there is this which you need to look into,
which has to do with, of course, overpopulation,
with global warming, etc., etc.
So, in other words, the questions are always there.
Many architects are highly responsible.
It's society itself that has perhaps forgotten to ask the questions.
Today, if you want to build, you're playing a double game.
Let me give you an anecdote which has nothing to do but everything to do with our
discussion.
It's an invented anecdote.
When Einstein, Albert Einstein, walks down my street in New York City 20 years or 40
years from now, when there was a lot of mugging,
a mugger takes his gun and points the gun at the head of Albert Einstein and asks
him, what time is it?
Is Einstein going to give him the theory of relativity?
No, he tells him what time it is.
Nevertheless, what he really does is the theory of relativity.
I think we find ourselves as architects always in this predicament.
We're talking in 2014, and the amount of recycling of Cedric,
of Cedric, which I see, and what the French call
a recuperation, using Cedric in every possible means
to justify things which are absolutely not worth it.
I would be very, very cautious at this sort of
refashionable packaging of Cedric Price.
I think there is a raw strength and, how can I say, I was almost going to use the
word honesty,
in the work. And it is often, I see it used by people who use it shamelessly for
purely commercial
purposes? Well, generally when you teach, when you talk to students, you're trying
to
make them understand that architecture is a mode of thinking and therefore you use a
set of examples.
amusingly enough the period between 1965 and 1975, 1980, was perhaps for political
reasons,
certainly for political reasons, certainly for economic reasons, there was not very
much work,
there was the whole question that went around the 68 period, there was the
disenchantment
in relationship to the modernist ideals and the disenchantment in relationship to
what was
proposed instead, in other words historicist postmodernist, hence the idea of trying
to
reinvent another world from other, you know, from another point of view, was
important. And I'll end with my, you know, my first point, which had to do with the
mode of notations. The language, the way you write the question, the way you do
those diagrams, the way you do those small cartoons, it's a way to come
to the heart of the ideas. It is not simply to do those great, you know, blue
skies and those lovely people running among the flowers. I was one of the
students representative at the ETH in Zurich. That was somewhere around 67, I
suspect and we were asked to suggest the name of lecturers and I was familiar, a
little familiar, I read some of the magazines, Architectural Design, AD and
so on and I was really interested in hearing Cedric come so I asked my
professors and they said no way this is not architecture so I kept a long story
short I succeeded a couple years later to invite him in an
independent venue called the Le Corbusier pavilion in Zurich but
But meanwhile I got to know Cedric, I went to see him several times in London, and
eventually
was interested to start to work for him.
He actually offered me a job, provided that the job that he was waiting for would
come.
It did come, but three years later, and by that time I was teaching at the AA and I
was
already doing my own work, it was a little late, but that meant that a very
different attitude was made available to someone like myself who had
been until then being educated in a very solid manner, but in a way which
was far more traditional than the role of the architect asking the questions as
as opposed to the architect answering the question.